(relaxed techno music)
- [Instructor] Let us now learn
how the budget constraint
changes with income and prices.
What happens when income
goes up or goes down,
and what happens if
prices go up or go down?
Remember,
the budget constraint is line
that goes from one intercept
to the other intercept
in the axis of Good 1, horizontally,
and Good 2, vertical.
Remember as well that the triangle area
below the budget line
collects or represents
all the bundles of Good 1
and Good 2 that this
consumer can purchase,
that this consumer can afford.
So let's see if income were to change
or prices were to change.
Remember, we have seen that
the value constraint
has two intercepts,
one in the horizontal axis,
another one in the vertical axis.
In the horizontal axis,
the intercept is given by the
ratio of income divided by P1,
and in the vertical axis,
the intercept is given by the ratio
of income divided by
the price of Good 2, P2.
So
if income
were to be higher,
let's say it went to go up to be M prime
that is higher than the
initial or original income M,
what would happen with
the budget constraint?
Because
income is in the intercepts,
both of them in the numerator, then
as income goes up, then the whole ratio
in both intercepts will go up.
Therefore, the new budget line
that will emerge out of
this increase in income
will look like this.
That is the intercepts in both
axis will be higher than initially.
So the budget constraint will,
or the budget line will shift rightwards.
If income instead
would have decreased,
then the budget lines
would have shifted inwards.
That is the budget constraint
would've become smaller.
It is something similar what
happens when prices change.
Suppose we have an initial budget line,
like the one is depicted here in green,
where as we know, intercept
is M divided by P1
for the horizontal axis, Good 1.
And in the vertical axis for Good 2,
it would be M divided by P2.
Those two would be the intercepts.
Suppose now that the price
of the first good goes down,
meaning the new price,
P1 prime, is smaller
than the initial value of P1.
In other words, P1 is decreasing.
If this is the case, then
since P1 is a denominator,
as P1 goes down or decreases,
then the whole ratio will go up,
therefore, the intercept
will now be higher.
But P1 is not in the
vertical or the intercept
for Good X2, therefore this intercept here
will not change.
So this one in the
horizontal axis will change,
will become bigger, but the intercept
in the vertical axis for
Good 2 will not change.
Therefore, the new budget
line will look like this.
It will be a rotation outwards
with respect to the original one,
and the income is the same,
so the numerator is same,
but the the denominator changes
and is smaller,
and it's this.
It is because the denominator is smaller
that this whole ratio has increased.
That is that the budget
line when P1 decreased
has rotated outwards in the
way depicted by the arrow.
Let us see how all these changes
can be seen in a dynamic graph.
So in this dynamic graph,
we will have the three factors.
Income will have price one,
and we have price two.
So let's start with a simple value of
income approximately around 100.
So there you go, 101.
And we're gonna have,
we're gonna start as a simple value
for the prices of these goods.
Let's put both of them around four.
We got it.
So this is gonna be, again, around 100.
Sorry, well, I couldn't get it 100,
but I get it 104, which is fine because
the intercept is well calculated
by when prices are four
and income is 104, the intercepts
will be M divided by P1, which is 26,
as you can see here.
And the intercept in the vertical axis
will be also M divided by P2,
104 divided by 4, also 26.
So now let's see what would happen
as we have seen
on the iPad, if income goes up,
both inter intercepts will increase,
therefore the whole budget
line will shift outwards.
See?
For income 142, intercepts
will become 36 in both sides.
If I instead decrease income,
the budget line shrinks, shrinks, shrinks
because both intercepts also
become smaller and smaller.
All right, so what
would happen if instead,
prices were to change?
So let's start with price one.
As we have seen, if we reduce
the budget line, it
would reduce price one,
the budget line will
rotate outwards shifting
oh, sorry, rotating outwards
increasing or by increasing its intercept
in the axis, in the X-axis.
If instead price one
were to increase, then
the intercept in the horizontal axis
will decrease because the intercepts M
divided by P1 and it would become smaller,
therefore, it's a rotation inwards.
What happens if instead P2 changes?
Maybe pause the video and think about it.
If the rotation
when P1 changes was by
shifting or by moving the,
by changing the intercept in the X-axis,
what would happen if we change the price
that affects the vertical
axis, the Y-axis?
Maybe you guessed it right.
If you increase the price,
the intercept will go down
along the vertical axis,
and if you decrease the price,
the intercept, of course, becomes
way higher or increases.
So it's a
flip side rotation
that would happen with P1.
Again, let's do just one time.
This is the kind of change
you will see in budget lines.
When income decreases, increases,
this is the kind of change you would see
and the budget line only
change in the intercept.
If P1 is changing, is the
only thing that is changing.
And this is the kind of
change you will see in the
Y-axis in the intercept
for Good 2 if P2 changes.
In some, when incoming increases,
the budget constraint shift
outwards in a parallel manner.
Remember, the slope of the budget line
was the ratio of minus P1 divided by P2,
income is not in that slope,
therefore, whatever changes
cost by increases or decreases in income
will not affect the slope.
And that is why the budget constraint
is shifting outwards
in a parallel manner,
like this.
The opposite happens if
income decreases, right?
The budget line will shift always inwards,
again, in a parallel manner.
And it is an important question to also
ask which one is better for the consumer.
And at this point,
although we have not seen
the consumer's preferences,
it is safe to say that typically,
for a typical consumer, a
higher income will be preferred
or will bring higher welfare or wellbeing
or satisfaction to the consumer
simply because we know
that when income is higher,
a larger amount of
bundles can be afforded.
This is the summary when P1 increases.
When P1 increases, the
slope of the budget line
gets deeper, first.
Second, the increase
in the price will pivot
the budget constraint inward,
as we have seen in the dynamic graph.
Increasing prices will reduce
the set of bundles that
the consumer can afford
and therefore typically will,
or an expectation will decrease
the wellbeing of the consumer,
or more typically will decrease
the wellbeing of the consumer.
But we will discuss those topics
related to satisfaction
and wellbeing later.